Inventory of the Gregory Family Papers 1829-1920
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Gregory Family Papers 1829-1920 1880-1900
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2008.138
0.30
The Gregory Family Papers follow the family of Virginia Governor John Munford Gregory and wife Amanda Wallace through three generations with letters dating from the 1820’s to the 1920’s. Most items are letters between family members and grant insight into the daily activities and concerns of the Gregory family. The collection also includes correspondence between members of the Gregory family and other acquaintances, including members of the John Tyler family. While most letters are of a personal nature, some also touch on the issues of politics, education, religion, and agriculture. The collection is rich in genealogical information on the Gregory family and related Croshaw, Graves, West, and White families, as well as history of the family’s war involvement. In addition to letters, the collection includes newspaper articles, family documents, and two diaries kept by John M. Gregory’s daughter, Mattie Galbraith, in the late 1870’s. There are also seven cased images of members of the Gregory Family, including Amanda Wallace Gregory, Amanda's sister (Elizabeth Christie Powell), William Wallace Gregory, and Mary "Mollie" Gregory.
Galbraith, Martha, 1851 - 1924; Gregory, Evelyn "Eva", circa 1840; Gregory, John M. II, 1804-1884; Gregory, John M. III, circa 1840; Gregory, Martha "Amanda", 1809 - 1894 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center from Letitia Gregory Galbraith Machado on 12/16/2008.
Biographical Note
Martha "Mattie" Gregory was born in Charles City County in 1851 to Judge John Munford Gregory and Amanda Wallace Gregory. In 1879, she married Robert Davidson Galbraith and relocated to Spartanburg, SC. She and her husband had five children, though only two (Letitia "Letty" Gregory Galbraith and John Munford Gregory "Greg" Galbraith) survived to adulthood. Mattie Galbraith died in 1924.
Scope and Contents
The Gregory Family Papers follow the family of Virginia Governor John Munford Gregory and wife Amanda Wallace through three generations with letters dating from the 1820’s to the 1920’s. Most items are letters between family members and grant insight into the daily activities and concerns of the Gregory family. The collection also includes correspondence between members of the Gregory family and other acquaintances, including members of the John Tyler family. While most letters are of a personal nature, some also touch on the issues of politics, education, religion, and agriculture. The collection is rich in genealogical information on the Gregory family and related Croshaw, Graves, West, and White families, as well as history of the family’s war involvement. In addition to letters, the collection includes newspaper articles, family documents, and two diaries kept by John M. Gregory’s daughter, Mattie Galbraith, in the late 1870’s. There are also seven cased images of members of the Gregory Family, including Amanda Wallace Gregory, Amanda's sister (Elizabeth Christie Powell), William Wallace Gregory, and Mary "Mollie" Gregory.
Arrangement of Materials
In order by recipient, when applicable, otherwise in order by subject matter. Then, within folder, in chronological order.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Family Name:
Galbraith family.; Gregory family.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Diaries; Newspapers
Geographic Name:
Charles City County (Va.)--History--19th century.; Virginia--Genealogy; Virginia--History--19th century.
Occupation:
Virginia. Governor (1842-1843: Gregory)
Topical Term:
College of William and Mary--History--19th century.; College of William and Mary--Students.; James City County (Va.)--History--19th century.; Legal documents.; Suisun (Calif.)--History.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1900.; Women--Virginia--Social life and customs.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence, 1829-1920; id56794
  - Letters to Letty Galbraith, 1893-1920; id56803 (Folder 1)
  - Letters to Mattie Galbraith, 1884-1918; id56805 (Folder 2)
  - Letters to Robert Davidson Galbraith, 1879-1892; id56807 (Folder 3)
  - Letters to Amanda Wallace Gregory, 1829-1894; id56808 (Folder 4)
  - Letters to John M. Gregory, 1843-1883; id56809 (Folder 5)
  - Letters to Letty Gregory, 1873-1902; id56810 (Folder 6)
  - Letters to Other (or Unidentified) Gregory Family Members, 1869-1909; id56811 (Folder 7)
  - Lettters to Thomas and William Wallace, 1832-1833; id56812 (Folder 8)
- Genealogical Notes, id56796
  - id57011 (Folder 9)
- Gregory Family Documents, 1847-1907; id56797
  - id57012 (Folder 10)
- Gregory Family Deaths, 1884-1903; id56798
  - id57013 (Folder 11)
- Newspaper Articles, 1903-1904; id56799
  - id57014 (Folder 12)
- Diaries of Mattie Gregory Galbraith, 1876-1881; id56929
  - Mattie Gregory Galbraith Diary, 1876-1878; id56930 (Folder 13)
  - Mattie Gregory Galbraith Diary, 1878-1881; id56931 (Folder 14)
- Photographs, id57010
  - Gregory Family Photographs, 1856-1870; id57015 (Folder 15)